朋友们
ladies and gentlemen
掌声有请Mr.JB
please welcome judith bishop
下午好
good afternoon everybody
继续开会
welcome back to the plenary session of the Microsoft faculty summit
有请leslie lamport
it's my great pleasure to introduce to you today
lamport 现在是微软的（2013）
Leslie Lamport who's a principal researcher at our Microsoft Research Silicon Valley Lab
咱们这些教员和学生
so students and faculty who have taught operating systems courses
从事计算机相关的这些人
as well as anybody who's really used a computer
都从lamport的工作中获益良多
will have benefited from Leslie's work
你就比如 逻辑时钟、安全与活性、序列化一致性（paxos）
on logical clocks 、safety and liveness 、sequential consistency
还有老多了
and many other parts of operating systems
这些在某方面奠定了计算机世界的理论
which laid the basis for the safe operation of the computers that we have today
在个人电脑OR大型分布式集群中发挥着作用
as they moved from the single desktop to the large number of interconnected devices we have
来微软前
Leslie before he joined Microsoft was a member of certain various prestigious institutions
leslie的履历就很传奇了
he was at MIT 、at Brandis University and at companies such as Dec 、Compaq and SR I
职业生涯中已经取得了各种荣誉和证明
in his career he has also received several honorary doctorates
但仍致力于帮助科学家发掘工作之美
and he has tried very hard to help scientists see their works’s beautiful
为此，他创造了一些东西
and for that purpose he also developed something
比如 LaTeX
that I think you all know very well which is let ik
他现在致力于帮助我们
he's now going to go on and try and persuade engineers
发现另一些真香的东西
that there's something else that is beautiful in life
那就是数学
which is mathematics and
即今日之话题
that's what he's going to talk to us about today
那么，掌声有请
so ladies and gentlemen please put your hands together
今年（2013）的图灵奖得主
for this year's am Turing Award winner
Leslie Lamport
感谢老铁
Thank You Judith
thinking above the code（主题）
thinking above the code
先说为啥思考
why do we think
思考助你成事
well it helps us do most things
比如打猎、盖房、写代码
like hunting a saber-toothed tiger or building a house or writing a program
那么啥时候该思考
so when should we think
对打猎来说，出发前
well hunting a saber-toothed tiger we should think before leaving the cave
也就是被老虎发现前就应该思考
when the tiger is charging at you
不然就完了
it's a little late
盖房前就该思考
building a house before beginning construction
当然
you don't want to think about what you're doing
请个建筑师
when the Carpenters are putting the roof on
来代替我们思考也行
allready start thinking about what you're doing
写代码前应该思考
writing a program we should be thinking before we start writing any code
那么怎么思考，how？
how to think
我最喜欢Mr.CG说的一句话
when I favorite quotes is from the cartoonist Guindon
”空想不如写下来“
who says writing is nature's way of letting you know how sloppy your thinking is
真正的思考不是空想，是写下来
to think to really think you have to write
如果只是拍脑袋
if you're thinking without writing
那你是在骗自己
chances are you're fooling yourself
是在假装思考
we're only pretending to think
思考的时候该写什么？
what to write？
对狩猎为生的上古
well hunting a saber-toothed tiger
打猎非常危险，因为那时的人还不会写
writing wasn't invented then which meant it was a very dangerous activity
对盖房来说
building a house
你应该先整个蓝图
well what'd you write before you build to start building a house are called blueprints
蓝色的图
and it's called drawing blueprints
对写程序来说
writing a program
coding之前也应该整个蓝图
well you should also write a blueprint of your program
讲专业一点，那叫规范
but blueprints of programs are what we call specifications
Specifications
specifications
计算机人总是恐惧规范
well when I say the word people tend to panic
因为这东西（规范）太正式了，看不懂
this formal stuff that's impossible to read and understand
一大堆概念啊公式啊意向啊把人绕蒙了
and you have to learn these funny symbols and all that sort of stuff
来看这个蓝图，足够复杂
yeah this is a blueprint you know all these complicated stuff going on
但不是所有的蓝图都让人头大
but this is also a blueprint
用光谱来表示蓝图的复杂度
in fact there's an entire spectrum of blueprints
一边是复杂度拉满
ranging from very detailed complicated blueprints
比如造这个桥需要的蓝图
which you need if you're building something that's very big and complicated
另一边
at the other end
可能只是个草图
they're just rough sketch of what you're building is just something you know really simple
对小项目，足以
that you're gonna do in the weekend
中间是一些典型的蓝图
and there are these ordinary blueprints for
房子啊什么的
you know things like a house or the stuff
这些东西的蓝图我们应该都见过
that kinds of blueprints that most of us might have seen
同样的，对规范来说，也有光谱
and similarly there's a spectrum of specifications
我们有贼正式的规范
there are formal specifications
特别正式
and on the other end of the your formal specifications
你得用精准的语言描述
written in a in a precise formal language
另一边，可以是简短的规范
and on the other end there are just short prose specifications
中间的，我称之为可数学描述的规范
and in the middle are what I like to call mathematical prose
大多数code足够简单，两句话就能描述明白
most code is really simple few sentences of prose will do
还有一些code，需要稍微花点心思描述
some code is subtle will requires more thought
不用多正式，但你得小心描述
and for that you have to write it ’s prose but it's it try to be you need to be pretty precise
最后剩下复杂的code
and some code is either very complex or very subtle or critical
特别是在
and that's especially the case if what you're doing
涉及到并发和分布式的项目中
is writing concurrent or distributed system
复杂的code需要你花心思去构思
it is going to be complex and subtle and quite likely critical
没有工具的话，这事就会非常烦人
and for that you should have tools
如果使用工具来帮助我们
you should be using tools
那就简单且安全
to check it to check your blueprints
使用故居意味着我们需要一种正式的语言
and if you're going to use tools it means you need a formal language
因为工具可不懂小作文
because tools don't understand prose
那么，怎么写一个规范
so how to write a spec
首先，要多想
well writing requires thinking
那么写代码要怎么多想呢
so how to think about programs
那就是像科学家一样思考
we should think about programs like computer scientists namely like scientists
我们都知道科学的思考非常有用
scientific thinking is a very successful way of thinking we know all that it's brought us
具体一点就是构建数学模型
what science does is make mathematical models of reality
来看天文学的成功例子
for example the first very successful science was astronomy
真实的星球有海洋、陆地等
the reality planets have mountains oceans tides and weather
太复杂不利于研究
and all sorts of complicating things
于是天文学家将其
but the simple model that's gotten astronomy pretty far
抽象为一个有坐标有质量的点
is to think of a planet model the planet as a point mass having position and momentum
计算机科学中有很多设备
computer science the reality consists of digital systems
处理器、手柄
things like a processor chip 、a game console or a computer executing a program
执行程序的电脑等
this is what I'll be talking about computer is executing programs
这些东西都可被抽象（被model）
but what I have to say applies to all those other things just as well
图灵机中
so models there are lots of models that you've probably come across
也有很多抽象（models）
Turing machines partially ordered set of events you probably haven't run across that
但是对我而言，就两个model最有用
and lots of models but - to my mind stand out as being the most useful basic models
函数和状态序列
functions and sequences of states
我们把一段程序看做函数
so functions we model a function of a we can model a program as a function
具体的，他是一个输入到输出的映射
that map's an input or to an output
可能一个多个输入到一个输出，也可能没有输入输出
or multiple inputs - or possible inputs to possible outputs
数学上的函数非常简单
in math the function is very simple
即函数是有序对（input->output）的集合
it's an order as a set of ordered pairs
来看自然数上得平方函数
so for example the square function on natural numbers
它由这样的配对构成 0-> 0 、1-> 1 、2-> 4
it's this set of ordered pairs this pair 0-> 0 、1-> 1 、2-> 4 etc
具体来看2->4
and the element 2-> 4 is an element of this set of the fact that the outlet that
它被表示为
the pair 2-> 4 is an element of this square function is usually expressed
2的平方等于4
by saying square of 2 equals 4
定义域是所有pair中的第一个元素的集合
now the domain of of square the domain of a function are all the first elements of those pairs
这里平方函数的定义域就是0 1 2 3等
so for the square function the domain is the set number 0 1 2 & 3 etc
即自然数，常记作N
also known as the natural numbers that I like to write as n
定义函数的第一步是确定定义域
to specify to define a function what you do is you specify its domain
就像这里的平方函数的定义域是自然数
so to specify square we say the domain of square is equal to the set of Naturals
对定义域中的所有元素X
and for each element X in its domain
函数Square都
we specify what Square maps X to
将其映射为X的平方
and it maps the value X to x squared
这就是Square函数的定义
so that defines the square function
数学中的函数和程序中的函数不同
now functions in math are not the same as functions in programming languages
数学中更简单
math is much simpler
我不是程序语言专家
I'm not a programming language expert
所以我不太了解程序中的函数（function）
so I don't know what those things that programming languages
但我知道数学上
which is called functions are
函数更为简单
but I know what math is that methods are a lot simpler
函数模型非常有用
now the functions model will take you very far it's very useful
但是仍有限制
but there has limitations
它只是定义了程序该做什么，但没说怎么做
its limitation main limitation is that it specifies what a program does but not how it does it
例如，快排和冒泡都是排序算法
so for example quick sort and bubble sort compute the same function
但显然他们的实现是不同的
but they're very different programs
此外，一些程序压根没有输入输出
also some programs don't just map inputs to outputs
还有一些没有结果
some programs run forever well you know they may stop
也就是那些会一直运行的程序
before the the Sun explodes but it's useful to think of them it's running forever
比如操作系统，简单的将之抽象位函数是没有意义的
for example operating systems you can't specify an operating system as a function
因为它不是输入映射到输出的形式
because it doesn't map inputs to outputs
因为上述的这些限制，所以我不将规范定义为函数
so for that for those specifications use what I like to call
我称之为标准行为模型
the standard behavioral model
这样的话程序的执行被视为行为
in which a program execution is represented by a behavior
行为是一个状态序列
a behavior is a sequence of states
状态是变量的某一个赋值（即某一个时刻的值）
and a state is an assignment of values to variables
如此，程序可以抽象为行为集合
and a program is modeled by a set of behaviors
程序的所有执行都称为行为
which behaviors that represent all possible executions of the program
具体来看欧几里得算法
so for example let's look at Euclid's algorithm
一个你们都知道
an algorithm is just an abstract program
的算法
as you all undoubtedly know
它计算两个自然数m和n的最大公约数
it computes the greatest common divisor of two natural of two integers m and n
先初始化：x=m；y=n
by initializing x to m and y to m
然后大数减小数
and then it keeps subtracting the smaller from the larger
直到x=y
and when x and y are equal then it stops
这个相等的数就是最大公约数
because that x and y equals the GCD of M and n
来看一个例子 M=12 N=18
so for M = 12 and N = 18 there's just one possible behavior
初始化：x=12；y=18
it starts with a state in which that assigns 12 to X and 18 to Y
通过一步减法得到下一个状态
and then subtract the next state is obtained by
该减法描述为用xy中的大数减小数
subtracting the smaller one from the larger X from Y
next state：x=12；y=y-x=18-12=6
so you get reach a state where x equals 12 and y equals 18 minus 12 or 6
然后再次从xy中大数减小数
and in the next state you subtract the smaller which is y from the larger and you wind up in the state
next state：x=x-y=12-6=6；y=6
in which x equals 6 and y equals 6
此时x=y=6，最大公约数是6
and since x and y are equal you stop
简单吧
so it's very simple algorithm
它只有一种行为
it has just one possible behavior
好了，那我们怎么描述行为集合
so how do we describe a set of behaviors
首先，我先提个理论奥
well first of all there's a theorem
有行为集合B
that says any set B of behaviors
B有两个子集
is the conjunct the intersection of two sets
一个子集满足安全
a set of behaviors satisfying a safety property
一个子集满足活性
and a set of behaviors satisfying a liveness property
额，啥是安全，啥是活性
so what our safety and liveness
官方定义先不谈
well I'm not going to bother going into you know
简而言之，当程序的某一行为会出错退出时
the formal definitions but a safety property is false if and only if
我们就说它没有安全性
it can be violated at some point during the behavior
来看局部正确的例子
so partial correctness is an example
当得到期望之外的答案时，局部正确性被破坏
partial correctness is violated if the program stops with the wrong answer
在行为的某一点上
so that's some point in the behavior
属性被破坏了
you can tell that it that it the property was violated
这个点就是程序因错误而退出的点
the point at which the program stopped with the incorrect answer
再来看活性
the liveness property is one
为了判断程序是否满足活性
in which you need to see the complete behavior in order to know if it's false
你必须观察整个行为
or if it's not satisfied by the by the program
典型的例子是termination
classic example is termination
你不能仅仅通过观察一段程序
you can't tell that the program hasn't terminated
就说程序已经停止了
by looking at any finite piece of the program
你必须观察所有行为才能知道他是否停止了
you have to look at the entire behavior to know that it never terminates
因此我们用
so we satisfy specify a set of behaviors with by specifying a
安全和活性来定义行为集合
safety property and aliveness property
在实践中，安全性更为重要
now in practice specifying safety just turns out to be more important
因为这是最有可能发生错误的地方 而且往往更微妙
because that's where errors are most likely to occur and tend to be more subtle
活性也很重要
I mean liveness is important just not as important to safety
但时间关系，今天不谈
and so to save time I'm going to ignore aliveness today
只谈安全性
and just talk about safety
好，如何定义安全性
so how to specify a safety property
我们使用俩东西定义安全性
we specify it with two things
1. 可能的初始状态集合
the set of possible initial States
2. 步进到下一状态的关系
and the next state relation
步进关系描述了一个状态的所有先驱状态
which describes all possible successor states
好的，那我们该使用什么语言来描述这两个东西呢
of any state so what language should we use to write these things
想想科学家会怎么做
well let's act like scientists
科学家用啥语言
what language do mathema two scientists use
用数学
and the language is mathematics
最科学的语言
that's the language of science
他们用公式描述初态集合
so the set of initial states they're described by a formula
在欧几里得算法中，初态就是
so in Euclid's algorithm the set of initial States we initialize the initial state is one
(x=m)^(y=n)
in which X = M and Y = N
这就是用公式表示初态
so that is specified that initial state is specified by this formula
这里只有一种初态
and the only part this has only one it's only one possible initial state that satisfies that formula
步进关系依然使用公式表示
the next state relation is also described by a formula
为了描述它
and to describe it
我使用不带撇变量来描述当前状态或者初态
I'll use unprimed variables to talk about the current state or the first state of the pair
使用带撇变量来表示next state
and prime variables we're talking about the next state
好，我们来看欧几里得算法的步进关系
so let's look at the next state relation for Euclid's algorithm
有两种可能
there are two possibilities
x>y or x<y
either X is greater than Y or Y is greater than X
公式表示为
so that formula is going to be the
两个公式
disjunction of two of two formulas
看图别看字幕
if X is greater than Y then the new value of x prime
不行就暂停慢慢捋
is equal to what you get by subtracting Y from it
继续看图
so it's new value of x prime is equal to the old value of
X minus the old value of y
and the new value of X of Y is equal to the old value
如图，第一个公式描述了所有满足x>y
so that first formula is specified by all pairs of states satisfying X
的步进关系
greater than Y and in the initial state
in first state X prime equals x minus y
and y prime equals y were okay
自行体会
you understand what what I said
这描述了一种可能
and that describes one one possibility
来看另一种可能
or the disjunction of these formulas to the other case
看图
it's or what Y is greater than X in the first state
and the value of y the new state and the value of y in the old state minus
the value of x in the old state etc
好了，图上的这两个式子描述了欧几里得算法的步进关系
so this simple formula describes the next state ratio relation of Euclid's algorithm
具体来看其执行过程
so let's see how it works
从这两个式子怎么得出行为
how you get behaviors out of those two formulas
继续看图
well for example for an example I'll take em equal to 12 and N equals 18
so to get the initial state we look at the initial predicate s-- predicate
and we substitute 12 for m and 18 for n
for what for n rather and you see you under
that substitution there's only one pair of values x and y that satisfy this
relation x equals 12 and y equals 18
so to get the next state the second state
we apply the next state look formula
substituting 12 for x and 18 for y
and we do that notice that 12 greater than 18 is false and 18 greater than 12 is true
we'll false and anything is false so that first half of the formula is false
true in anything is people to the rest of the formula
so this formula is satisfied by the old value of x being 12
and the new value of x being 18 minus 12 or 6
so this is the only possible next state that satisfies this next relation
when for the initial state x equals 12 and y equals 18
okay to find the next state we do the same thing we
substitute 12 for X and wife and 6 for y
we simplify we see that 6 greater than 12 is false and 12 greater than 6 is true
so the formula simplifies to x prime equals 12 minus 6 and y prime equals 6
so it tells us that the only possible successor state
the only possible third state is x equals 6 and y equals 6 and to find the next state
well do the same thing we substitute 6 for X and 6 for y and we see
that the entire formula is false
and there are no values of x prime and y prime which can make the formula false true
so there is no next state
so there's no next state means the program is stopped
这就是欧几里得算法
so that's Euclid's algorithm
我们再来看看欧几里得算法
and when we see special about Euclid's algorithm is for any values of x and y
我们按照公式
there are unique values of x prime and y prime
总能找到对应的路径
that make next true
其中一条状态或者相等状态
there's either one value or no values
因此欧几里得算法是deterministic（有确定解）
so Euclid's algorithm is deterministic
那non-determinism呢？
to model their non determinism
我们就只有让步进关系
we just have a next state relation
允许当前状态可能有多个next state
that allows multiple next States for a current state
这可太难了
there's nothing magic you know terribly difficult
非确定解可太难了
you know hard about can about non determinism
变量的多重赋值
multiple assignments of values to prime variables
对于单个变量多重赋值以使next为真
that make next true for a single assignment of values to unprimed variables
这就是非确定解
that's what non determinism is all about
ok 那正式的规范呢？
okay what about formal specs
我们使用正式规范是为了使用工具
we need formal specifications only to apply tools
数学家在有工具之前
we mathematicians you know before there were any tools you know wrote math
记录数学信息
you know very you know an informal notation
他们想使用一种数学语言来记录
they want to use Mathematica though they have to you know write in the language Mathematica
因此我们需要使用一种规范语言来使用工具
so if we want to apply of tools we need a formal language
这就是
and the language that I'm going to describe were
TLA+
I use is called TLA plus
来看公式在TLA+中的表示
so this this pair of formulas are written just like this in TLA plus
我们需要一些声明
we need to form a language we need to write declarations
声明常量M和N，变量x和y
we declare m and n to be constants and x and y to be variables
然后界定边界，这里是都是整数
and then add a little boilerplate we said it extends the integers
或者是一些定义了加减大小的标准
the integer or a standard module that defines things like plus and minus and greater than
然后用一个MODULE括起来
and we put them inside of a module which I've called module Euclid
这就是欧几里得算法的TLA+规范
and that's a TL A+ specification of Euclid's algorithm
就这样
and this is what it looks like in SK
现在你可以检查这个规范
now you can model check TLA plus specs
模型检查是一种在小模型中检查所有可能的概念
know model checking conceptually checks all possible confusions of the program on a very small model
高效且简单
it's extremely effective and quite easy to do
你只需要简单的告诉checker模型的定义
you know you basically tell the model checker what the model is
模型通常是一些常量赋值
models are usually you know instantiating values of constants
在欧几里得算法中，我们需要告诉checker m和n是什么
so for Euclid's algorithm we'd have to tell it what m and n equals
然后他就开始检查
and then the model checker will go through
很快奥
and in you know a few nanoseconds
对一些简单的我们检查一种可能的行为
for something that simple will we'll check whoa b1 possible
你也可以写正式的正确性证明
their behavior and you can write formal correctness proofs
然后在TLA+中做检查
and check them mechanically in TLA
在TLA+中写证明
you know write the proofs in TLA plus
然后我们有定理证明器来检查这些证明
and we have a theorem prover that can check the proofs
这可老累了
and that's hard work and well all this is math stuff
所有这些数学上得东西都非常完美
we know he's you know it's really very well nice and pretty stuff
但数学的情况都非常理想
but we know that math works only for toy examples
为了对真实的系统进行抽象，你需要一个真实的语言
to model real system you need a real language
支持类型、构造器、对象等等
with types procedures objects and all of that
开玩笑！我们来引用以为Amazon工程师的话
ma'am wrong let me quote something written by Chris Newcomb as an Amazon engineer
“我们在10个线上项目上使用TLA+”
said we have used TL A+ on 10 large complex real-world systems
“每个项目里TLA都展现了非凡的价值”
in every case TL A+ has added significant value
“特别是在预防细微bug上”
either preventing subtle serious bugs from reaching production
“这给了我们足够的信心”
or giving us enough understanding and confidence
“去做更激进的性能优化而不用担心破坏正确性”
to make aggressive performance optimizations without sacrificing correctness
人们总会告诉你使用正式的规范
one of the other things people will tell you about formal methods is
会在性能上拖死你
oh if you use a formal method you're really going to kill your performance
但是事实正相反
well in fact it's just the opposite
他们还总说管理层不会允许的
and the other thing they'll tell you is Oh management will never let us do it
但Amazon的管理层现在正鼓励团队使用TLA+
well management at Amazon and now encouraging teams to write TL a-plus specs
他们在年度计划中规划使用TLA+的时间
and in annual planning managers are allocating engineering time to use TLA Plus
这是在2013年写的
this was written in 2013 I think there are a few more systems
应该还没有几个系统使用TLA+
that they've been specifying since then
xbox360内存团队
the xbox360 memory system
Chuck Thacker在Xbox内存系统的TLA plus spec有一个实习生
a Chuck Thacker had an intern right at TLA plus spec of the Xbox memory system
仅仅写了规范但没有做模型检查
and just writing the spec didn't even get to point of model checking it
他发现了一个bug
he caught a bug that the designers of the memory system at IBM
一个IBM工程师抓破脑袋后承认的bug
after scratching their heads looking at it said yeah that was a bug
一个没有被测试程序发现的bug
and that would not have been caught by their testing procedures
这个bug将会引起世界上所有的xbox一起瘫痪
and that bug would have caused every Xbox in the world to crash after four hours of use
你可以在web上学习TLA+
you can learn about TLA plus on the web
今天我不教TLA+
today I'm not going to be talking about TLA plus
我今天讲信息规范
I'm going to be talking about informal specifications
来看个例子
and I'll start with an example
TLA技术是TLA+的printer
TLA Tech which is the pretty printer for TL A+
这可能是某个使用TLA+的人写的规范
here is what somebody user TL A+ user might write
一些沙雕公式
some silly formula like this
如果在此基础上做些微小的工作
and if you just did the naive output
选一些字体，然后翻译成ASCII
just took things from teletype font and put them into translated the ascii into the symbols
把/\转换成^
left / right / into the conjunction symbol
就变成了右边的公式
and you get something like that formula and the right
对齐在TLA+中非常重要
but alignment is actually has significance in TL a-plus
没人喜欢右边的对齐方式
and the user undoubtedly wanted he certainly wanted the left conjunction symbols aligned
因为可能有歧义
because the formula might mean something different otherwise
并且人们确实希望等号是对齐的
and he also probably wanted those equal signs aligned
所以这是一个正面例子
so this is the right output that the pretty partition produce for this example
请看这个例子
on the other hand if you look at this input
它的naive格式为
this is what the naive output would be like
这两种都没人喜欢
and the user probably didn't want those two symbols aligned
oh 完蛋
that was probably just an accidental
所以在这个例子中，右边的正确
so in this case the naive output is the correct output that's what you want
也就是说我们对对齐这件事没有准确的定义
well there's no precise definition of correct alignment
准确的定义有用户决定
correctness means what the user wants
要用户来确定的事那就是不确定
and there's no way of formally specifying what the user wants
所以很明显 如果我们可以指定正确性规范
so obviously if we can specify correctness specification
我们需要什么样的规范才能说明正确性
what good can specification we need to specify correctness
我们如何使用规范
what could how can we use specification
是的我们可以
well we can
不知道一个程序应该做什么并不意味着你不必思考
not knowing what a program should do doesn't mean you don't have to think you just do this code
它意味着你要多想
it means you have to think a lot harder
也就是说规范在你不知道code是干啥时
which means that that's what a spec is even more important
更为重要
when you don't know what the program is supposed to do
规范描述了code应该做什么
and it seems impossible to even say what it should do
因为你要决定code应该做什么
because it has to do something and you have to decide what it should do
所以你要多想，多写
so that requires a lot of thinking which requires writing
我就是这样做的
so what did I do
我的规范有6条规则
well my spec consisted of six rules plus definitions
他们是带信息的数学片段
and these are in informal met you know quote mathematical prose
他们在注释中
and formal if they're written in comments
来看其中一条
oh here's an example of one of the rules
它说左注释标记是与其覆盖标记对齐的左注释
it says a left comment token is left comment aligned with its covering token
lamport也不知道这rule干啥的
well I don't even know what that means anymore
我得看看说明书
I'd have to read the spec
但是左注释对齐和覆盖标记是术语
but left comment aligned and covering token are terms
在我编写的本规范中定义的
that were defined in the in this specification I wrote
如果你看它 这是真正的数学散文
and if you look at it this is really mathematical prose
我写了什么这个规范 它更容易理解和调试六个规则
what did I write this spec well it was a lot easier to understand and debug six rules
超过850行的代码 也可能超过850行
than 850 lines of code probably would have been more than 850 lines of code
如果不是我先写了这些规则
if I hadn't written those rules first
我对规则做了很多调试
and I did a lot of debugging of the rules
你写了一堆规则
you know you write a bunch of rules
但是他们是干啥的并不明显
and you know what they're going to do is not obvious
你试了一堆例子 试了一个调试代码
and you try a bunch of examples and I a debugging code
这样我就可以看到应用了什么规则
so I could see what rules were being applied
我们不会做一些奇怪的事情 然后说 这条规则需要修改
and we don't would do with something weird and I say oh and that rule needs to be modified
对于这个迭代过程
for this and an iterative process
少数的错误和规则的实现很容易被发现
and the few bugs and implementing the rules were easy to catch
虽然没有问题
though there was no problem
如果我刚写了代码
had I just written the code
我要花更长的时间才能找到我能忍受的东西
it would have taken me much longer to just get something I could live with
我确信结果不会产生如此好的格式
and I'm sure the results wouldn't have produced formatting nearly as good
那么为什么不是一个正式的规范呢 为什么我不在TLA+spec上写呢
so why not a formal spec why didn't I write at TLA + spec
几个原因
well several reasons
首先 并不一定需要格式
first of all getting it right was not that important
世界不会因为
the world is not going to come crashing
有些东西没有很好地对齐和漂亮的打印而崩溃
down if something isn't quite properly aligned and pretty printing
特别是 它也不一定在所有情况下都漂亮
in particular it didn't have to work in all corner cases
没有一条路是完全正确的
yes No you know there's no way of getting it you know totally right
重要的是没有任何工具
and just as important there aren't any tools
可以帮助我，模型检查器在这个例子中没有帮助
that could help me the model checker wouldn't have helped in this example
因为你需要一些属性来检查它
because you know you need some some properties to check it against
他们只是工具
and you know they're just tools were not
TLA plus工具不是为这类问题而设计的
you know the TLA plus tools are not designed for that kind of problems
那么这个规范的典型特征是什么
so what's typical about this spec
规范在代码之上
the spec is at a higher level than the code
规范可被任何语言实现
it could have been implemented in any language
没有方法也没有工具没有你最喜欢的编程方法
no method nor tool none of your favorite ways of you know programming methodologies
在这里一文不值
would have been worth a damn here
对写规范的一点帮助都没有
they would not have helped me write the spec
因为不论是什么方法
because no method of writing you know better code
规范都同样重要
would have made the spec unnecessary
我得写规范而不是code
I had to write the spec it was not code
规范可没说你怎么实现
and it says nothing about how to write the code you could implement my spec in any language
写规范是帮助你思考
you write a spec to help you think about the problem before you think about the code
那么这个规范的不典型之处是什么呢
so what's not typical about this spec
写的含糊不清
it's quite subtle
记得我说过95%的代码只需要更少的思考
remember I said 95% of code people write requires less thought
更简单更短的规格足够好了
and you know simpler shorter specs good enough
直接写一套规则
also it's a set of rules
一组规则 需求或公理通常是一个糟糕的规范
a set of rules or requirements or axioms is usually a bad spec
因为这真的很难理解
because it's really hard to understand
事实上，它很好的解释了特殊问题
it turns out that that was a good match for this particular problem
这意味着没有关于如何编写规范的通用规则
which says there are no universal rules about how to write specs
没有万能的规则可以告诉你如何编写任何程序
no universal rules that'll tell you how to write any program in the world
那么定义怎么去计算一个函数
so specifying how to compute a function
定义怎么打印是难得
specifying what the pretty printer should do is hard
实现规范是容易的
implementing the spec was easy
定义一个排序程序是简单地
specifying what a sorting program should do is easy
弄清楚如何有效地实现它是很困难的
figuring out how to implement it efficiently is hard
没人告诉你咋整
at least if nobody has showed you how
这需要你思考，需要写规范
it requires thinking which requires writing a specification
来看快排的规范
so I'll give you an example of a specification for quicksort
大家都知道快排
probably you all seen quicksort
快排是典型的减而治之算法
quicksort is written by Tony Hoare it's a divide-and-conquer algorithm
为了排序一个数组
for sorting an array
从A[0]到A[n-1]
call it a zero to a n minus one
简单起见，A是一个number数组
and for simplicity I'll assume that's an array of numbers
快排使用partition进程，来从lo到hi-1之间
and it uses a partition procedure you give it two arguments low and high
选择一个pivot point
and what that procedure does is it chooses a pivot point
pivot number in low to high minus 1
然后交换A[lo]和A[hi]
and then it permutes the elements to the left of the pivot a low to a high
使得
it permutes the number the the part of the array within the limit from low to high
所有轴点左边小于等于轴点
so that everything from pivot downwards
is becomes is less than or equal to
所有轴点右边大于轴点
everything from pivot plus 1 upwards
得益于我们都知道快排
so fortunately if well seen quick sort before
所以导播掐一下这段快排的描述
so i rambling description isn't necessary
说重点，我不关心怎么实现
and for this example I don't care how this procedure is implemented
当然 怎么实现是快排的核心
of course that's the real trick of quicksort implementing
但我只有50min
that but you know I only have 50 minutes here so
所以我们用伪代码来描述快排
so let's specify quicksort and pseudocode
看图
you know this by the partition procedure is pick a pivot and low-to-high -1 and
permute a low to a high to make bla bla
bla and return the value pivot
然后递归之
and you have a recursive procedure q s applied to low to high
and if low is less than high
you call the protection procedure for on low and high
and then you recursively call the procedure for the 2 subintervals
and if low is not less than high then it means you have one element
and there's nothing to sort and so you're done
and the main program just implies QS to the entire array from Sirte and minus one
没有那些繁琐的东西
so informal no formal syntax no declarations pseudocode
伪代码是一种很好的规范
it's it's a fine specification yeah when
你可以根据伪代码写好code
you're gonna code you know pretty trivial to code from this
用任何语言
and you know any programming language
都行
easy to understand
但这真的够快么
but it's a really quick sort
这是快排的平凡描述
it's the way quicksort is almost always described
但是递归可不是快排的必要部分
but recursion is not a form fundamental part of quicksort
减而治之只有一种实现方式
it's just one way of implementing divide and conquer
这就有问题了
now here's a problem
事实上，递归不是最好的方式
and in fact it's probably not the best way
如果你在多个核心上使用该算法
if you want to execute this on multiple cores
留个作业
so here's a problem give to your friends and colleagues
写一个非递归形式的快排
write a non recursive version of quicksort
好像没人可以在10分钟内写出来
almost no one can do it in ten minutes
受递归版本的影响
they try to compile the recursive version
没人可以
and nobody can get
没人可以在10分钟内写出来
almost nobody can get that right and ten minutes standing on their feet
我来告诉你正确的方法
but I'll tell you you know what the real solution is
我们要做的是维护一个带索引的集合U
we do is maintain a set u of index ranges
partition作用于这个集合
on which partition needs to be called
U的初始状态是整个待排数组的范围（0到n-1）
initially u equals contain is a set containing a single index range
从0到N-1
from zero and minus one represented by this pair
现在我们写伪代码
now we can write this in pseudocode
但是想想科学家怎么做，让我们写下初态和步进公式
but let's be scientists let's write init and next directly in mathematics
所以有如下假设
so the initial predicate
设A是长度为N的number数组
says a is equal to any array of numbers of length n
U是一些元素的集合
and u is equal to the set consisting of that single element
在数学上这不够正式
yep this is in formal mathematics but it's informal you know
我们可以正式点
we could write some formal way of describing the set of a on any array of numbers of length N
在写步进前做一些定义
and before writing next let me make a definition
定义Partitions(B,pivot,lo,hi)
let me define partitions of B pivot low high
参数表示B的一个子集
it's the set of arrays obtained from B
即B[lo] 到B[hi]
by permuting the load to be high
使用pivot分区
with pivot point pivot in other words
即partition程序作用的集合
it's the set of all values that the partition procedure
Patition函数在这个子集中
the set of all new values of a that
找轴点并且返回
the partition procedure is allowed to return
在如果需要返回轴点的情况
if it's also returning pivot as the pivot point
简单起见我就不写了
and I won't bother writing it out precisely
所以步进关系表示的事U的旧值到新值的关系
so next remember it's going to be a relation between the old values of a of U
新值带撇
and the new values a prime and u Prime
我们试着写一下
so let's write it
首先，如果是空集
first of all we're gonna stop
我们应该stop
if u is the empty set
所以步进关系说，U应该不是空的
so the next state relation says U is not equal to the empty set
看图
and so performing there's going to be false if u is the empty set
然后我们选择U中的任意一对B T 如果B
then we pick any pair BT in U and if B
不等于T,那么我们选择B中的任意点P,任意数P
is not equal to T then we pick any point P any number P lying in B to t minus 1
我们让旧值是
and we let a prime be any element of
通过Partition得到的合法分区
the set of legal partitions you know the
一组合法分区中的任意值
results of the partition function that
如果你把b和t当做输入
if you've given it B and T as the input
返回轴点p
and it returns P as the partition as the
pivot point and then u prime is a set u
我们完成剩余的元素bT
we're finished with the remain element bT
所以我们把它从集合中移开 然后加上2个子区间
so we move that from the set and then we add the 2 subintervals
B P and you know to be and P plus 1 to T
into the set u of of ranges that still need to be sorted
otherwise if B is not e is equal to T then there's nothing to do
we leave a prime unchanged and we let u prime equal u with BT removed
we just take BT out of out of the set
and that's the next state relation
这就是快排的迭代版本
that describes a very nice way of doing quicksort iterative iteratively
这实际上是跟平凡的实现
it's actually a more general algorithm because if you
你看整个执行过程
look at all the behaviors that can produce
递归只是子集
the set of behaviors produced by the recursive version is a sub set
这是所有值序列的集合
that is the set of all sequences of values
假设它是一个子集
that a assumes is going to be a subset
下一个状态关系所允许的
of the ones that this next state relation allows
所以为什么几乎没人发现这个版本呢
so why can almost no one find this version of quicksort
因为人们的思维陷在code里
because people's minds are stuck in code
没有在code之上思考code
they haven't thought learn to think at a higher level than the code
现在可以很容易的写出准确公式
now it's easy to write this as a precise formula
pick any arbitrary value is really existential quantification
the formula is true if there exists a value B T and u similarly there
and just let letting a prime be any element of this set
现在足够简单了
well that's easy enough to write
is a prime and an element of that
and those relations new values of U prime those thinks the
with prose to the right of the equal sign
they're easy to express
whoops this way and so on then
现在你有一个完美的TLA+公式
so what you have is a TLA plus formula here perfectly formal
如果你还是喜欢伪代码
if you prefer pseudocode
我们也有Plus cal， 它想一种玩具语言
we have plus Cal it looks like a toy programming language
算法实际上出现在注释和TLA plus模块中 而是一个表达式
and the algorithm in fact appears in a comment and TLA plus module but an expression
可以是任何TLA加表达式
can be any TLA plus expression
它也有一些非决定论的构造
it also has some constructs for non determinism
但事实上它可以是任何TLA
but the fact that it can be any TLA
表达式可以是任何TLA plus表达式
an expression can be any TLA plus expression
这意味着任何数学表达式
which means any expression of mathematics
都使他更具表达性
makes it enormously powerful more more expressive than
任何编程语言设计者梦寐以求的东西
anything any programming language designer has ever dreamed of
它被编译成一个易于理解的TLA plus规范
and it gets compiled to an easy-to-understand TLA plus spec
事实上 我经常用plus cal写东西
and in fact I regularly write things in plus cal
当我证明它们的正确性时
and then when I'm proving the correctness of them
我直接对TLA plus规范进行推理
I reason directly about the TLA plus specification
你喜欢TLA plus工具模型检查器
and you like the TLA plus tools the model checker
和定理证明器到加号到平移
and theorem prover to the plus to the translation
永远运行的程序一直在谈论计算函数的程序
programs that run forever have been talking about programs that compute a function
永远运行的程序通常涉及并发
programs that run forever usually involve concurrency
像操作系统 分布式系统之类的东西
things like operating systems distributed systems
很少有人能把它们做对
few people can get them right
通过思考和写作
by just thinking and writing
我不是他们中的一员
I'm not one of them
我们需要工具来检查我们在做什么
we need tools to check what we're doing
TLA plus对亚马逊工程师如此有用的原因是
the reason the TLA plus was so useful to the Amazon engineers is
因为模型检查器
because the model checker
因此 对于并发和分布式系统 您需要编写一些内容
so for concurrent and distributed systems you need to write something
您可以使用TLA plus或plus Cal 它是为分布式系统设计的
you use TLA plus or plus Cal it was designed for distributed systems
很好用 你不会轻易写出对的 分布式并发算法
it's great and you're not gonna get it you know distributed concurrent algorithm right
如果不进行模型检查
if you don't model check
如果它已经用完了 你不需要写一个规范并检查它
it it's spent you don't write a specification and check it
其他95%非常简单的东西就是一个例子
the other 95% really simple stuff here is an example
你知道我在程序中写的规范
of a spec you know that I write wrote in a program
我为什么要写那个规范
why did I write that spec
为了确保我在编写代码之前知道代码应该做什么
to be sure I knew what the code should do before writing it
没有真正的写 我只认为它应该做什么是显而易见的
without writing aspect only thought it was obvious what it should do
我必须编写规范 以确保它确实简单明了
I had to write the spec to be sure it was really as simple and as obvious
正如我所想的那样
as I thought it was
后来我不用读代码了
and later I didn't have to read the code
想知道我写的那段代码做了什么
to know what that piece of code I wrote did
我刚写了说明书可以看说明书
I just wrote the specification could read the specification
所以一个一般规则 这是一个规则 至少我们可以说 一般规格
so a general rule that's one rule at least we can say about specs in general
如果您正在编写代码应该做什么规范
if you're writing a spec of what a code should do
一段代码应该做什么
what a piece of code should do
这应该说明了任何人使用代码所需要知道的一切
that should say everything that anyone needs to know to use the code
在我刚刚展示的示例中 代码是如何工作的
how the code worked in the example I've just showed
只是太简单了 不需要一个规格
was just too simple to require a spec
我是说这比我想象的要难
I mean it was it turned out to be harder than I thought
当我开始编码时 我会发现
I would have discovered that when I started coding
我会停止编码 写一个又一个规范
and I would have stopped coding and wrote and written a specification
那么程序员应该知道什么是思考
so what programmers should know about thinking
每个人都应该知道的思考
what everyone should know about thinking
每个人都认为他们认为
everyone thinks they think
但是如果你不写下你的想法
but if you don't write down your thoughts
你在自欺欺人
you're fooling yourself
关于思考 程序员应该知道什么
what programmers should know about thinking
你在编写代码之前应该先思考
is that you should think before you code
这意味着您应该在编写代码之前编写
which means you should write before you code
说明书就是你在code前写的东西
a spec is simply what you write before coading
所以什么教练 你知道我说的代码是什么意思 你应该具体说明什么
so what coach you know what do I mean by code what should you specify
基本上 其他人可能想要使用或修改的任何一段代码
basically any piece of code that someone else might want to use or modifying
一个月后别人很可能就是你
and that somebody else is likely to be you in a month
当你忘记了你写的这段代码是做什么的时候
when you've forgotten what this piece of code you've written does
它可以是整个程序或系统或类或方法
it could be an entire program or system a class a method
只是方法内部的一段棘手的代码
just a tricky piece of code inside of a method
关于代码 您应该指定什么
what should you specify about the code
他应该是什么
what it does
这意味着所有人使用它所需要知道的一切
which means everything anyone needs to know to use it
还有它可能的做法
and perhaps how it does it
如果它是复杂的 微妙的 你需要努力思考 以使他正常的工作
if it's complicated subtle you need to think hard about in order to get it right
这有时被称为算法
this is you know what's sometimes called an algorithm
或者高级设计
or a high-level design
您应该如何考虑或指定高于代码级别的代码
how should you think about or specify your code above the code level
在状态和行为方面
in terms of states and behaviors or
输入输出关系函数
functions for input output relations
应该用数学方法来做
should do it mathematically
在必要的情况下 尽可能的严谨和非正式
as rigorously informally as is necessary
你应该用数学思维
you should be thinking mathematically
即使你写的是非常非正式的数学
even if you're writing thing the mathematics very informally
可能使用伪代码或plus Cal
perhaps with pseudocode or pass or plus Cal
如果你在说明某件事是如何发生的
if you're specifying how something does it
那么 如何学习编写规范呢
so how do you learn to write specs
通过编写正式的规范 即使你没有
by writing formal specs even if you don't
即使您在生活中从来不需要编写完全正式的规范
even if you never need to write a completely formal spec in your life
学习编写正式的规范将真正帮助你学习编写非正式的规范
learning to write formal specs will really help you learn to write the informal specs
你需要写的
that you need to write
你通过编写程序 运行程序和纠正错误来学习编写程序
you learn to write programs by writing them running them and correcting your errors
您可以通过编写并运行规范来学习编写正式规范
you can learn to write formal specs by writing them running them
用一个模型检查器来纠正你的错误
with a model checker and correcting your errors
现在TL A+可能不是最适合你的语言
now TL A+ may not be the best language for you
我肯定它不是最好的正式语言
you know it's I'm sure it's not the best language for formal language
对于世界上每一种规格
for every kind of specification in the world
任何语言都不能
no language can be
对于你的特殊需求 它可能不是你所知道的最好的语言形式
it may not be the best form of language you know for what your particular needs are
但我知道这对
but I do know that it's great for
学会数学思考是很棒的
learning to think mathematically
所以除非你能找到更好的方法来做这件事 否则你应该使用TLA plus
so unless you can find something better for doing that you know which works use TL a plus
你知道学习TLA+
you know learn TL a plus
学会数学思考
learn to think mathematically
如何将规范与代码连接起来
how do you connect the spec to the code
好吧 你有连接数学概念和它们的实现的注释
well you have comments connecting mathematical concepts and their implementation
例如 数学概念可能
for example the mathematical concept might
是一个图形
be a graph
实现可能是一个节点对象数组和一个链接对象数组
and the implementation would be an array of node objects and an array of link objects
在这方面 特别是另一种说明书
in this connection the other specification especially
如果是非正式的规范 应该在注释中
if it's an informal specification should be in the comments
也应该解释这些数学
and so should the explanation of how those mathematical
注释在代码中实现
comments are implemented in the code
那么编码呢
so what about coding
我的意思是 我们的程序涉及到编写代码 你必须编写代码
I mean we're programs involve writing code you have to write code
关于写代码我没什么好说的
I have nothing to say about writing code
我说的没有任何暗示
nothing I said implies anything
在编写代码时 您仍然需要思考
you still have to think while you code
这意味着你必须一边写一边编码
which means you have to write while you're coding
但是你在编码的时候是正确的
but what you're right while you're coding is is code
我对你应该如何编码没什么可说的
and I have nothing to say about how you should code
使用任何你想要的编程语言
use any programming language you want
任何编程方法
any programming methodology
你仍然你仍然要测试和调试你的程序
you still you're still going to have to test and debug your program
这不是一个好的写作方面 我们要捕捉编码错误
not this good writing aspect is we're going to catch coding errors
因为这与编码无关
because it's not about coding
它会捕捉算法错误
it'll catch algorithm errors
编写规范是另外一个步骤
writing specs is an additional step
并且可以通过及早发现错误来节省时间
and it may save time by catching errors early
当他们更容易纠正，但不绝对
when they're easier to correct no promises there
它肯定会提高你的编程能力
it certainly will improve you programming
所以你会写出更好的程序
so you'll be writing better programs
为什么程序员不愿意写规范
why are programmers reluctant to write specs
尽管写作很难
well writing is hard writing is hard
思考更难
in fact because thinking is hard
你知道没有通往数学的捷径
you know there's no Royal Road to mathematics
好像是阿基米德说的
as who wasn't who said that Archimedes I think
为什么写作很难 因为写作需要思考
why is writing hard well because writing requires thinking
而思考很难
and thinking is hard
就像我说的 你更容易认为你在思考
and as I said it's easier to think you're thinking
写作很像跑步
writing is a lot like running
除非你做得慢一点
unless you do it slower you are
你必须加强你的写作能力
and you have to strengthen your writing muscles
你知道就像你必须加强你的意志
you know just like you have to strengthen your rust
和你的肌肉，这需要练习
and you're running muscles it takes practice
找个借口不这么做更容易
and it's easier to find an excuse not to
还有一个最好的借口 如果规格是错误的呢
and one of the nicest excuses well what if the spec is wrong
也许你在说明书上弄错了
maybe you made a mistake in the spec
也许需求在哪里改变了
maybe the requirements change where
需要进行一些改进
some enhancement is needed
事实上 代码将不得不改变 甚至在程序完成之前
in fact and the code will have to be changed maybe even before the program is finished
事实上 更改代码
in fact changing the code is something that
最终会发生在所有有用的程序上
eventually happens to all useful programs
你的程序很有用
your program is useful
它会有用户 用户会找到他们想要的东西
it's gonna have users the users are going to find things extra things they want of it
那些不能正常工作的事情
the things that don't work the way
从客户视角考虑是个好想法
you know you thought was a good idea be your customers
否则这种情况最终会发生在所有有用的程序
you know decide otherwise this happens eventually happens to all useful programs
在一个理想的世界里 你会写一个新的规范
in an ideal world you'd write a new spec
然后你知道代码 你会完全重写规范的规范
and then you know the code you'd completely rewrite the spec of the spec
我们都知道这是不可能的
well we all know this isn't gonna happen
在现实世界中 代码是打补丁的
in the real world the code is patched
如果你幸运的话 规范更新了
and if you're lucky the spec is updated
好吧 如果这是不可避免的 为什么要费心写规格在第一位
well if this is inevitable why bother writing specs in the first place
如果这个小可爱（规范）
if you know this little lovely thing is
不得不改变
you know the spec turns out you know - has to be changed and you know
我们又回到了过去那个乱七八糟的世界
we're back in our old messy world
有两个原因
well there's two reasons
第一个原因是无论是不得不修改代码的谁
the first reason is that whoever has to modify the code
都将永远感激你所写的每一个字或每一个公式
will be eternally grateful for every word or formula of specification that you write
不管是谁 也许你 相信我 你这样做了 然后你回头看
and whoever maybe you believe me I've you've done that you know coming back
没有时间听第二个故事
and don't have time for second stories
特别是修改和漂亮的印刷 事实上
but particularly you know modifications and the pretty print or in fact
这就是为什么在更改代码时应该更新规范的原因
and that's why you should update the spec when you change the code
第二个原因是每次代码被修补
the second reason is that every time code is patched
它变得更难看 更难理解 更难维护
it becomes a little uglier harder to understand and harder to maintain
但是如果你不从一个规范开始你写的每一段代码
and if you but if you don't start with a spec every piece of code you write
都将成为补丁 这意味着程序从头开始
is a patch which means the program starts out from the beginning
难看 难以理解 难以理解
being ugly hard to understand and hard
当你需要维持的时候 只能祈求上帝
to maintain and then God help you when you do have to maintain
帮你知道这段代码是啥意思
you know try to unfit out what it's doing in order to to
正如德怀特·艾森豪威尔所说
make changes as Dwight Eisenhower said
计划决定不了战争的胜负
no battle was ever won according to plan
但战争的胜利离不开计划
but no battle was ever won with that one
所以有些人会告诉你
so some people will tell you that
写规格是浪费时间
writing specs is a waste of time
在某些情况下可能确实这样
in some situations and maybe
有时候你不需要去想你在做什么 也许有些事情真的很琐碎
sometimes there's no need to think about what you're doing maybe something is really so trivial
不需要太多思考
that you know doesn't need much thought
但是当他们告诉你不要写规范的时候 我们得知道
but we'll remember when they're telling you not to write a spec
他们其实是告诉你不要思考
they're telling really telling you not to think
可你知道思考是一个很好的主意
and you know thinking is a really good idea
不要相信任何告诉你不要这样做的人
and don't trust anybody who tells you not to do it
思考并不能保证你不会犯错误
thinking doesn't guarantee that you won't make mistakes
但是不思考通常保证你会
but not thinking generally guarantees that you will
了解有关TLA plus的更多信息请访问我的主页并单击TLA网页的链接
find out more about TLA plus go to my home page and click on the link to the TLA web page
感谢
thank you
[Applause]
Q&A环节
I think there's time for a few questions
时间比较紧
very few I think
one yeah yes
我希望这不是对我讲话的评判
I hope that's not a judgment on my talk
thanks for your talk
怎么看规范在
how about specification by example
测试驱动开发启发的实用方法下的应用呢
it's a pragmatic approach that is a little bit inspired by test-driven development
当然 因为它还不完整
which since it's not complete of course
但是因为完备性无论如何都是不可判定的
but since completeness anyway is undecidable
这是一个很好的实用方法 所以你知道吗
it's a good pragmatic approach so do you know
如此糟糕的务实方法也许是个好方法
so terrible pragmatic approach it's maybe a good
也许这是一个很好的方法来解释什么东西 例子很好地解释了它们
maybe a good way to explain what something examples are great to explain them
但它们很可怕它们让你无法思考
but they're terrible they keep you from thinking
从这些特殊的例子来看
you think in terms of these particular examples
编程中真正的问题是不要去想那些简单的例子和显而易见的例子
the real problem in programming is not to think of your the easy cases the obvious cases
好例子，hard例子
the nice case if the hard cases
你不能用例子来理解
and you don't get that with examples
我会告诉你我曾经eclipse编程
and boy I'll tell you I used to eclipse programming
我知道有这么多这么多的eclipse方法
and I've you know there's so much so many methods of eclipse
下面是一个使用它的代码示例
that are explained by here's an here's an example of code using it
我还没有设法用这些方法来做我想做的事
and I have yet to manage to use those methods to do it what I want to do
因为它不起作用 我发现除了这个例子之外 它对其他任何东西都不起作用
because it doesn't work I find that it just doesn't work on anything other than that example
并且我束手无策
and I have no idea why not
不是一个你知道的通过例子编程的程序
not a program you know programming by example
我不知道这是否有效
I don't know about you know if that works
但举例说明却没有
but a specification by example it doesn't
谢谢你的精彩演讲
thank you for the great talk um
那么一旦你修补了代码 会发生什么呢
so what happens once you patch the code
你建议保留旧的规格还是
do you suggest keeping the old specs around or
还是直接删了
do you just get rid of him
比如有上下文有帮助吗
like does it help to have context
首先 我认为每当我修复错误 这可能需要改变规范
well first of all I think whenever I well whenever I do fix bugs and that may require changing the spec
我还会记下我为什么要更改规范
I will also take a note as to why I change the spec
因为你知道两年后我会回来
because you know two years later I'm going to come back
然后说我为什么要这么做
and say why did I do that
是否这在多大程度上是有用的
about whether you know to what extent that's useful
对于规范本身我不知道
for the specification itself I don't know
当然 不扔掉任何东西总是个好主意
certainly you're always a good idea not to throw anything away
不应该扔掉
you know we shouldn't be throwing you know information away these days you know
又不占地方，留着呗
it doesn't cost anything to save it so you should certainly save the old specs
你是否应该知道
whether you should you know
至于你是否应该在新规范中记录更改
whether you should mention the change in the
我也没
in the new spec I don't I don't have any
啥确定的答案
any good answer to that
我不想无礼 我认为大多数程序员
without wanting to be rude or anything I think most programmers
不再使用正式的规范
don't use formal specifications anymore
我的博士就是在这个背景下
my PhD was in that background
现在大多数程序员 他们采用算法 他们采用代码
most programmers these days they take algorithms they take code
他们根据自己想做的事情来调整
they adapt it to what they want to do
从我的角度来看 这是99%的
and that's 99 percent is from my perspective
软件是这样构建的
how most software is built these days
那很好啊 如果它
that we actually really be nice if it
如果那样就完事了那很好啊
if that where it can build Bell built well that way
它不起作用 因为他们试图使用
it doesn't work because they're trying to use
我发现它不起作用是因为其他代码
I find that it doesn't work because the other pieces of code
那些没有规范的其他代码
that I want to use don't have specifications
所以我真的不能很好地使用它们
so I really can't use them very well
我尽力了
I do the best I can
我老卷了，花了老鼻子时间在
and I wind up having to spend a hell of a lot of time
试图明白那段代码干啥的
trying to figure out what this piece of code does
但如果有规范，我就不必这么累
which something I shouldn't have to do if it had been specified
我再说一遍 你知道95%的编程
again I've said that you know 95% of programming
只需要很少的规格
you know requires very little specification
几行通常就足够了
and you know a few lines you know are usually enough
但还有5%
but you know you are going to come up with this 5%
这不仅仅是把东西放在一块
which isn't just you know take this thing and put it here
连上他们
and combine it with this thing
你得写一些代码
there's gonna be something some things code you're gonna have to write
这是微妙的 它有点困难
that is subtle it has some some a bit of difficulty in it
你想为此做好准备
and you want to be able to you know you want to be prepared for that
因为我们使用同样的技术
because we use the same techniques that
和同样的思想漏洞
you use you're the same lack of thought
当你做其他95%的事情时
that you use when you're doing that other 95%
你会搞砸的
you're gonna screw up badly
不幸的是 我从来没有真正研究过TLA plus
unfortunately I have never really looked into TLA plus
但是研究了时态逻辑之后 不可避免地会注意不到这一点
but having studied temporal logic it is inevitable to to fail to to notice that
有很多时间逻辑
that there's a lot of temporal logic
在你所说的底层
going on underlying what you've been saying
所以我想知道你有没有研究过也许你有可能
so I was wondering have you studied probably you have the possibilities
更直接地使用时态逻辑的语言
for using more directly the language of temporal logic
未来将作为必要性运营商和所有的东西 所以
will future operates as necessity operators and all that stuff and so
ok TLA代表动作的时序逻辑
ok TLA stands for the temporal logic of actions
时序逻辑是邪恶的
temporal logic is evil
我可以告诉你解释为什么 因为它很难使用
I can tell you explain why because it's very hard to use
但事实证明这是一种必要的罪恶
but it turns out it's a necessary evil
时序逻辑被证明是思考活力的最佳方式
temporal logic turns out to be the best way of thinking about liveness
所以如果你使用TLA plus当你到达活性部分时
and so if you use TLA plus when you get to the liveness part you're
将使用时序逻辑 并注意到这一点
going to be using temporal logic and be aware of it
但请记住 我说过安全更重要 事实证明 你不需要思考
but remember that I said that safety is more important and it turns out that you do not need to think
你不需要知道时态逻辑
you got not need to know temporal logic
为了处理安全问题
in order to handle safety
我想你们知道TL A+比其他时序逻辑更好的原因是什么
and what the reason I think you know that TL A+ is better than other kinds of temporal logic
为了安全起见 使用它基本上不需要时序逻辑
is that you need-to-know essentially no temporal logic to use it for safety
如果你看看实际的规格
if you look at the actual specification
这有具体的TLA规范
there is the specific the TLA specification I've noticed
我已经写好了 里面有两个公式 下一个
I've written it it's two formulas in it and next
TLA允许您将它们组合成一个单一的时序逻辑公式
well TLA allows you to combine them into a single temporal logic formula
你知道你最终会这样做
which you you know you do at the end eventually
但是它的伟大之处在于
and but the idea of the thing it makes it great is that
你要写一千行的规范 999行是普通的数学
you'll write a thousand line specification 999 lines are going to be ordinary math
初态 步进关系 然后最后一行是一个时态逻辑公式
initial predicate next state relation and then the last line is going to be a temporal logic formula
所以好吧
so okay
我们没有
well do we have no
因此 我们的全体会议现在已经结束
so we are now at the end of our plenary session
我非常感谢你 但在此之前
and I'd like to thank you very much but before we do that
我得告诉你去哪吃
just to remind you all we got the buses outside to go out to the dinner tonight
带走随身垃圾
take your bags with you there will be space there for your bags
然后去哪住
and then we'll be going back to the hotels or coming back here and
感谢Leslie
now thank you very much Leslie
[Applause]